Finding aid for Interlochen Center for The Arts Records, 1927-2005
Bentley Historical Library
- Chronological, 1920-1966
  - Subject Files, 1928-1989
    - Camp, 1928-1989
      - Application forms
        - Intermediate, 1944-1989 (Box 41)
        - All State, 1957 (Box 41)
        - College/University, 1941-1966 (Box 41)
      - Calendars/class schedules
        - General, 1935-1967; 2 folders (Box 41)
        - High school, 1934-1989 (Box 41)
        - Intermediate, 1948-1989 (Box 41)
        - Junior, 1960-1969 (Box 41)
        - Orchestra (pre-college), 1955-1972 (Box 41)
        - College/University, 1938-1960 (Box 41)
      - Camper and Parent information
        - Equipment lists, 1939-1961 (Box 41)
        - General, 1946-1972 (Box 41)
        - Non-college, 1946-1964 (Box 41)
        - College, 1934-1961 (Box 41)
      - Course materials
        - Electronics, 1947-1948 (Box 41)
        - Music laboratory, 1958-1960 (Box 41)
        - Opera, 1946; 1954; 1963 (Box 41)
        - Strings (Maddy)
          - Violin and Violas, 1944; 1949 (Box 41)
          - String class teaching, 1957-1961 (Box 41)
            (see also Box 38 Interlochen-Publicity-Movies)
          - String Workshop, 1965 (Box 41)
      - Directors' meeting, minutes, 1985 (Box 41)
      - Enrollment statistics and analyses (Maddy)
        - General, 1938-1947 (Box 42)
        - Student application analysis, circa, 1947 (Box 42)
        - General, 1948-1965; 3 folders (Box 42)
      - Faculty
        - Instructions and memos, 1947-1972 (Box 42)
        - Lists of, 1945-1969 (Box 42)
      - Interlochen List (recommended numbers)
        - Correspondence, 1946-1952 (Box 42)
        - Printed, 1946; 1947; 1949; 1953; 1963 (Box 42)
      - Library (music, instruments and equipment)
        - Orchestra library to date, 1934 (Box 42)
        - American works, 1940(?) (Box 42)
        - Papers, 1945-1966; 3 folders (Box 42)
        - Music performed 1967-1968 (American) and 1976, 1967-1976 (Box 42)
        - Catalogues, 1956-1958 (Box 42)
      - Medical, 1945; 1961 (Box 42)
      - Programs
        - First assemblies, 1962-1964 (Box 42)
        - Final assemblies, 1948-1965 (Box 42)
        - Concerts, 1946-1982 (Box 42)
      - Reports and recommendations
        - General, 1938-1965; 3 folders (Box 42)
        - Activities
          - Crafts
            - Coordinator, 1961-1968; 5 folders (Box 42)
            - High School Girls, 1965-1968; 2 folders (Box 42)
            - Intermediate Girls, 1965-1966 (Box 42)
            - Junior Girls, 1965-1966 (Box 42)
            - Junior-Intermediate Boys, 1960-1968; 2 folders (Box 42)
          - Recreation
            - High School Girls, 1960 (Box 42)
            - High School Girls, 1961-1966; 6 folders (Box 43)
            - Intermediate Girls
              - Section I, 1962-1965 (Box 43)
              - Section II, 1963-1964; 2 folders (Box 43)
          - Theatre Arts (Drama), 1963-1966; 2 folders (Box 43)
          - Waterfront
            - High School Girls, 1962-1965; 1968; 4 folders (Box 43)
        - Junior Girls, 1966Divisions
          - Recreation High School Boys, 1964 (Box 43)
          - High School Girls
            - General (materials distributed), 1966 (Box 43)
            - Section II, 1963-1966 (Box 43)
            - Section III, 1961; 1964-1967; 4 folders (Box 43)
          - Intermediate Girls
            - Section II, 1964; 1966; 2 folders (Box 43)
          - Junior Girls, 1966 (Box 44)
          - University
            - All State
              - General, 1965-1967 (Box 44)
              - Girls, 1965 (Box 44)
            - Dean of Women, 1960-1967 (Box 44)
        - Miscellaneous
          - Camp Hostess, 1974 (Box 44)
          - Information Center, 1974 (Box 44)
      - Roster of Campers, 1933-66; 1987-1989; 4 folders (Box 44)
      - Scholarship information, 1940-1969
        - Application forms, 1937-1956 (scattered) (Box 44)
      - Staff
        - Memos and instructions, 1951-1972 (Box 44)
        - Counselors' manuals
          - General, 1949-1962 (Box 44)
          - Girls Divisions, 1952; 1961 (Box 44)
      - Student
        - Government, 1946-1966 (Box 44)
        - Poems and songs, undated (Box 44)
      - Transportation (rail), 1947-1961 (Box 44)
    - Academy, 1940-1976
      - Planning papers
        - General, circa, 1946-1962; 2 folders (Box 44)
        - Ten Hoor, Martin
          - Correspondence, 1956-1968; 3 folders (Box 44)
          - "Thoughts on" proposal, 1957 (Box 44)
          - "Prospectus", 1958 (Box 44)
          - Reactions to Prospectus, 1958-1959 (Box 45)
          - Headmastership correspondence, 1958-1959 (Box 45)
        - Implementation
          - Cary Potter report, May, 1959 (Box 45)
          - Preliminary survey, June-July, 1959
            - Committee meeting, June 1959 (Box 45)
            - George Ebeling correspondence (Box 45)
            - Clyde Vroman working files, 8 folders (Box 45)
            - Report, July 1959 (Box 45)
            - Supplement to report, interviews conducted (Box 45)
          - Curriculum conference, July 1959 (Box 45)
          - Progress report, August 1959 (Box 45)
          - Progress report, October 1959 (Box 45)
          - Curriculum conference papers, 1959-1960 (Box 45)
          - Joseph W. Cohen, consultant, 1960 (Box 45)
          - Gillis papers on development and funding, 1960-1961 (Box 45)
          - Curriculum conference, 1961 (Box 45)
          - W. Clement Stone's thoughts, September 1961 (Box 45)
          - Preliminary report (Ralph West), November 1961 (Box 45)
          - Maddy planning files, circa, 1960-1962
            - Academy bulletins (Box 45)
            - Buildings and equipment
              - Audio-visual (Box 45)
              - Classroom building (Box 45)
              - General (Box 45)
              - Science Laboratories-cost analysis (Box 45)
            - Calendar Study (Box 45)
            - Educating the gifted child, articles (Box 45)
            - Faculty (Box 45)
            - Finances (Box 45)
            - Headmaster (Box 45)
            - Student recruitment and enrollment
              - General, 1960-1962 (Box 45)
              - Form responses, 1962 (Box 45)
      - Operation
        - General
          - Articles of Incorporation, 1960; 1963 (Box 45)
          - Maddy papers, 1962-1965 (Box 45)
            (See also Box 21-Speeches)
          - Faculty, 1962-1965 (Box 45)
          - Guest conductors, 1963-1964 (Box 45)
          - Repertoire lists, 1963-1966 (Box 45)
        - Opening convocation, September 1962 (Box 45)
        - Yearly operating files
          - 1962-1976, 16 folders (Box 45)
        - Reports for Independent Schools Association
          - Self Evaluation, February 16-18, 1976 (Box 87)
          - Committee report, February 16-19, 1976 (Box 87)
    - College
      Interlochen (Subject) College of Creative Arts contains planning materials, 1966-1968. They include the prospectus for the college, which Maddy submitted a month before his death, and subsequent follow-up materials. Researchers should also check the indexed correspondence for Alden Dow, who did the architectural planning for the college, as well as the Post-Maddy Administrators Karl Haas and Boards Trustees sub-subseries during the late 1960's and early 1970's.
      The yearly operational files, 1962-1976, include mainly mimeographed items but also some correspondence and, in the early years, Maddy notes. Information on off-campus tours can be found in Interlochen "Special Events" of this sub-subseries, and Maddy speeches in Subject Maddy "Publications." Researchers interested in the history of the Academy should also consult Printed-Articles, Scrapbooks, Post-Maddy Administrators, especially Haas and Jacobi, Boards-Trustees, and Post-Maddy Administrators.
      - Prospectus (by Maddy), March, 1966 (Box 87)
      - Papers, 1967-1968 (Box 87)
      - Development fund, printed, 1967-1968 (Box 87)
  - Later Acquisition, 1930-2005
    The second subseries, 1930-2003, Later Acquisition, contains records that were received in the year 2005 as an addition to the existing record group. Some duplication of materials from the previous accession may exist. However, an effort was made to eliminate such files, and researchers are encouraged to check this subseries for records that are believed to be unique regarding topics such as the early development of the camp, Maddy's correspondence, and Maddy's funeral. There are also materials relating to events that occurred at a later date than are represented in the files belonging to the earlier acquisition. Especially interesting are the Special Events and News Releases subseries.
    - Alumni
      - Correspondence from "distinguished alumni", 1984 (Box 87)
      - Early formation of alumni association, 1965-1967 (Box 87)
    - Campus
      - List of Buildings, 1966 (Box 87)
      - IAA Survey Report, 1959 (Box 87)
      - Estimate of Physical Needs for Establishment of Interlochen Arts Academy, 1959 (Box 87)
      - Gardner Group IT Report, 2000 (Box 87)
      - Long Range Plan for the Campus, 1991 (Box 87)
      - Master Plan for the Campus, 1991 (Box 87)
      - Program and Design Criteria: Music Building, Theatre Arts Building, Campus Center, 1994 (Box 87)
    - Course descriptions/schedules
      - IAA Class Schedule, 1996-1997 (Box 87)
      - IAA Course Description and Fee Schedule, 1997-1998 (Box 87)
      - IAA Course Description and Fee Schedule, 1999-2000 (Box 87)
      - IAA Class Schedule, 1999-2000 (Box 87)
    - Curriculum
      - Curricular Improvement Project Report, 1965-1968 (Box 87)
      - Preliminary Report on Curriculum Conference, 1960 (Box 87)
      - Meeting with consultants, 1959 (Box 87)
      - Misc. interviews regarding the curriculum, 1959
        - Lawrence Conrey, Science (Box 87)
        - Paul Hunsicker, Physical Education (Box 87)
        - Professor Hutchroft, Industrial Arts (Box 87)
        - Phil Jones, Mathematics (Box 87)
        - William Merhab, Foreign Languages (Box 87)
        - Nicholas Schreibner, Principal, Ann Arbor High School (Box 87)
        - Kenneth Vance, Library Consultant (Box 87)
        - Scott Westerman, Social Sciences (Box 87)
        - Fred Wolcott, Language Arts (Box 87)
      - Schedule of Curriculum Committee Meetings, 1961 (Box 87)
      - Correspondence with John Lemmer, consultant, 1961 (Box 87)
    - Education Policy Committee
      - Correspondence with Donald Currie and Charlotte Roe, 1987 (Box 87)
      - Sabbatical leave memos from Jacobi, 1982-1986 (Box 87)
      - Statement of Philosophy and relevant correspondence circa, 1975 (Box 87)
    - ESM (unidentified ruling body) minutes
      - Thru, 5/9/2001; 8/1/2001 (Box 87)
      - Thru, 8/1/2001; 1/9/2002 (Box 87)
      - Thru, 1/9/2002; 7/31/2002 (Box 87)
    - Fact Sheets
      - 1990-1996 (Box 87)
    - Faculty/Staff Handbooks
      - 1991-1992 (Box 87)
      - 1997-1998 (Box 87)
    - Faculty/Staff Lists, 1991-1993 (Box 87)
    - Grainger, Percy
      - International Percy Grainger Society, board meeting minutes, 2000 (Box 87)
      - Publications of the Friends of Percy Grainger, 1999; 2000 (Box 87)
    - Henethorne, Margaret
      - Correspondence, 1987-1991 (Box 88)
      - Materials compiled as a working manual for assistant to the president, (left in original order), 2 folders (Box 88)
    - Honoraria (Box 88)
    - Interlochen Arts Academy self-studies
      - 1983, 2 folders (Box 88)
      - 1990 (Box 88)
      - 1994 (Box 88)
      - 1998 (Box 88)
      - 2000 (Box 88)
    - Interlochen Center for the Arts: Chapter 10 of the book Profiles of Excellence: Achieving Success in the Nonprofit Sector, 1991
    - International Arts Festival
      - 1998-1999, 4 folders (Box 88)
    - Issuance of financial bonds for campus renovations, 1996
      - Bond resolutions (Box 88)
      - Correspondence from the law office of Miller, Canfield, Paddock, and Stone regarding resolutions (Box 88)
      - Campus renovation project (Box 88)
    - Maddy, Joeseph
      - Correspondence
        - Capital Films (Box 88)
        - Chamber of Commerce, Traverse City (Box 88)
        - Complimentary letters (Box 88)
        - Complimentary letters-Prelude (Box 88)
        - Complimentary letters-received after Prelude (Box 88)
        - Bram notes (Box 88)
        - Browning, Norma Lee, Letter from Barbara Maddy (Box 88)
        - Family crest (Box 88)
        - Federation of Music Clubs, Illinois (Box 88)
        - Federation of Music Clubs, Michigan (Box 88)
        - Federation of Music Clubs, National (Box 88)
        - Federation of Music Clubs, Ohio (Box 88)
        - Federation of Music Clubs, Wisconsin (Box 88)
        - Federation of Music Clubs, 1959 (Box 89)
        - Ferguson memorial fund (Box 89)
        - Final camper list requests (Box 89)
        - General (Box 89)
        - Giddings estate (Box 89)
        - Gonzales (Box 89)
        - Guest conductors (Box 89)
        - Guests expected (Box 89)
        - Guests invited (Box 89)
        - Hanover Bank (Box 89)
        - Health department (Box 89)
        - Historic duplicates (Box 89)
        - Ogg, Russel (Box 89)
        - Jet air base (Box 89)
        - Kresge scholarships (Box 89)
        - Letters from foreign students (Box 89)
        - Notes (Box 89)
        - Music Educators National Conference, 2 folders (Box 89)
        - Michigan Music Educators Association (Box 89)
        - Michigan, State of (Box 89)
        - Music camps, other (Box 89)
        - National Music Council (Box 89)
        - Letters announcing Philips resignation (Box 89)
        - Pre and post camp groups (Box 89)
        - Publicity and promotion (Box 89)
        - Radio station (Box 89)
        - Radio, National Music Camp (Box 89)
        - Requests, miscellaneous (Box 89)
        - Scholarships (Box 89)
        - Season pass answers (Box 89)
        - Camp senate, 1959 (Box 89)
        - Sibelius letters (Box 89)
        - Stace -- to do (Box 89)
        - String Teachers Conference (Box 89)
        - Ten Hoor (Box 89)
        - Typewriters (Box 89)
        - United States Government (Box 89)
        - University of Michigan (Box 89)
        - West Michigan Tourist and Resort Association (Box 89)
        - White House (Box 89)
      - Miscellaneous
        - Biographical data for the Encyclopedia of American History (Box 89)
        - Funeral register (Box 89)
        - Letters sent in condolence to Mrs. Maddy (Box 89)
        - Letters Sent to Maddy in Hospital (Box 89)
        - License to operate the camp (Box 89)
        - Mrs. Maddy's replies to condolence letters (Box 89)
      - Writings
        - Autobiographical manuscript (Box 89)
        - Miscellaneous (Box 89)
        - Speeches (Box 89)
    - Michigan, State of
      - Correspondence with Department of Conservation regarding purchase of State lands and road construction (Box 89)
    - News Releases
      - News Releases, chronological
        - 1980-1982 (Box 89)
        - 1988, 1989 (Box 89)
        - 1991-1994 (Box 89)
        - 1995-1997 (Box 90)
      - News Releases, alphabetical
        - Achievement program (Box 90)
        - Awards, 1981-1982 (Box 90)
        - Arts School Network (Box 90)
        - Arts awards (Box 90)
        - Better Homes and Gardens (Box 90)
        - Brahms (Box 90)
        - Chamber music (Box 90)
        - College / Academy (Box 90)
        - College admissions statistics (Box 90)
        - Composer spectacular (Box 90)
        - Creative writing (Box 90)
        - Dance division (Box 90)
        - Detroit Symphony Orchestra (Box 90)
        - Drama division (Box 90)
        - Ecology (Box 90)
        - Entertainment Guide (Box 90)
        - Festival, 1982 (Box 90)
        - Four Fathers (Box 90)
        - Grants (Box 90)
        - IAA staff (Box 90)
        - Lyric Opera of Northern Michigan (Box 90)
        - Math department (Box 90)
        - Motor News (Box 90)
        - Murphy, Bob (Box 90)
        - National Federation of Music Clubs (Box 90)
        - National Merit Scholarship Competition (Box 90)
        - National Youth Writing Competition (Box 90)
        - Organ department (Box 90)
        - Outreach, 1981-1982 (Box 90)
        - Parks, Rosa (Box 90)
        - Percussion day (Box 90)
        - Playwright Project (Box 90)
        - Presidential scholars (Box 90)
        - Schutz, Heinrich (Box 90)
        - Seniors, 1982 (Box 90)
        - Special Contest Series (Box 90)
        - Success Magazine (Box 90)
        - Suzuki Magazine (Box 90)
        - Traverse the Magazine (Box 90)
        - Visual arts (Box 90)
        - Weekender (Box 90)
        - WIAA (Box 90)
    - Pathfinder school
      - Family Handbook, 2000-2001 (Box 90)
      - Kaleidoscope (Newsletter), 2000 (Box 90)
    - Petrillo/Mackinaw Bridge controversy, 1958 (Box 90)
    - President's reports
      - 1945-1960 (Box 90)
        (incomplete)
      - 1945-1947 (Box 90)
      - 1952-1958 (Box 90)
      - 1960 (Box 90)
    - Reports
      - Assessment of Institutional Advancement for the Interlochen Center for the Arts, 1992 (Box 90)
      - Interlochen Center for the Arts, annual reports, 1990-1992; 2001; 4 folders (Box 90)
      - Interlochen Center for the Arts Information Technology Consulting Report, Executive Summary, 1998 (Box 90)
      - Report for College Admissions, 1993; 1996 (Box 90)
      - Report on the Findings and Recommendations of the City/County Task Force on the Arts, 1985 (Box 90)
    - Special Events
      - General Motors National Concerto Competition, 1993 (Box 90)
      - Interlochen Symposium, 1987 (Box 90)
      - Jacobi Dinner, 1990
        (left in original order)
        - Publicity (Box 90)
        - Photos (Box 90)
        - Logistics (Box 90)
        - Memos re: Presidents Club and Corporate Council, etc. (Box 90)
        - Steuben/ Lansing Moore purchase orders (Box 90)
        - Correspondence (Boal) (Box 90)
        - Guest lists (Box 90)
        - Press clippings (Box 90)
      - Milliken Dinner, 1981
        - Supporting documentation (Box 91)
        - Correspondence
          - Jacobi (Box 91)
          - Pre-dinner (Box 91)
          - Post-dinner (Box 91)
        - Congratulatory letters for Milliken (Box 91)
        - Meeting minutes regarding: dinner (Box 91)
        - Guest lists (Box 91)
        - Ballroom information/plans (Box 91)
        - Programs, invitations, script (Box 91)
        - Film documentation (Box 91)
        - Press release (Box 91)
        - Financial (Box 91)
      - Orchestra Tour, 1986
        - Planning (Box 91)
        - Itinerary (Box 91)
        - Contracts (Box 91)
        - Debriefing and budget (Box 91)
        - Seating invitations (Box 91)
        - Balian reception (Box 91)
        - Washington correspondence (Box 91)
        - New York correspondence (Box 91)
        - Other performances (Box 91)
        - Support and thank yous (Box 91)
        - Publicity, newspaper articles, and photos (Box 91)
      - Osterlin Gala, 1993
        - Program (Box 91)
        - Invitation (Box 91)
        - Photographs (Box 91)
      - Pacific Rim Tour, 1997 (Box 91)
      - Richard Riley visit, 2000 (Box 91)
      - Karol Syzmanowski sculpture presentation, 1980 (Box 91)
      - Yanni visit, 1996 (Box 91)
    - Tolley
      - Correspondence
        - To, 1993-1995; 3 folders (Box 91)
        - From, 1994; 1995; 2 folders (Box 91)
    - Strategic Planning Update, 2000 (Box 91)
- Post-Maddy Administrators, 1958-1995
  The fourth series, Post-Maddy Administrators, contains records of individuals who knew and worked with Maddy and held important positions from the expansion of the late 1950's through 1989. It consists of six subseries: Donald Gillis, director of development (1958-1962), John A. Merrill, board secretary, administrative committee chairman, and vice president (1959-1969), Margaret A. "Peg" Stace, Maddy's long-time secretary (1942-1966) and eventual corporate secretary (1967-1973), George Wilson, director of the Camp (1957-1979) and acting president (1970-1971), Karl Haas, president (1967-1970), and Roger Jacobi, board secretary and director of personnel (1956-1959), director of the university division (1968-1971), and president (1971-1989). Researchers should also check the Subject and Boards series for correspondence and other information on their roles. Also included in the subseries are files that cover the period from 1989 on and the new generation of Interlochen leaders, who lacked ties to Maddy: Dean Boal, who succeeded Jacobi as president, Sheryl Szady, who played an important role in alumni activities, Richard Odell succeeding Boal, and Edward Downing succeeding Odell. Boal documents the first half of the Boal presidency (1989-1992) Szady the second half as well as the transition to the administration of Richard Odell (1992-1995). Odell covers his term of office (1995-1998) and Downing covers the first two years of his term (1998-2003).
  - Donald Gillis
    Donald Gillis, 1954-1962, contains personal background information and correspondence, including on his activities as a composer, but the great bulk concerns his administrative duties at Interlochen, 1958-1962. Much of the latter pertains to his leadership of the American Opera Theatre and publication of the Catalogue of American Operas. Included are correspondence, planning and promotional materials, and reports. The subject files detail his other activities at Interlochen. Researchers should also consult the Subject series for his role in planning the Academy as well as Interlochen: "Broadcasting," "Fund raising," "Interlochen Press," and the "Petrillo controversy." His later views on the institution, 1973-1977, can be found in the "Personal" section of Roger Jacobi in this subseries (F).
    - Personal
      - Articles and biographical (Box 46)
      - Correspondence files
        - General, 1958-1962 (Box 46)
        - Downs, Hugh, 1958-1961 (Box 46)
        - Snapp, Ken, 1960-1961 (Box 46)
    - Administration
      - Maddy correspondence, 1954-1961 (Box 46)
      - Trustees correspondence
        - General, 1958-1961 (Box 46)
        - Gordon, Britton, 1960-1961 (Box 46)
      - Trip reports (includes Maddy), 1959-1961 (Box 46)
      - Inter-office memoranda, 1959-1961 (Box 46)
    - Opera
      - American Opera Theatre
        - Planning
          - General, 1958-1961 (Box 46)
          - Reports, 1959-1960 (Box 46)
        - Promotion
          - General, 1958-1960 (Box 46)
          - Press, 1958-1959 (Box 46)
          - ASCAP (Paul Cunningham), 1958-1961 (Box 46)
          - Balendonck, Marie, 1959 (Box 46)
          - Broadcast Music Inc. (Oliver Daniel), 1958-1961 (Box 46)
          - Chappell & Co. (Irving Brown), 1958-1961 (Box 46)
          - Dunham, Edwin (NBC), 1959-1960 (Box 46)
          - Hauser, Arthur (Theodore Presser Co.), 1958-1960 (Box 46)
          - Johnson, Thor, 1958-1960 (Box 46)
          - Korn, Richard, 1958-1962 (Box 46)
          - McWhorter, Charles K., 1957-1961 (Box 46)
          - Mennin, Peter, 1959-1961 (Box 46)
          - Metropolitan Opera, 1959 (Box 46)
          - Music Clubs, National Federation of, 1959-1961 (Box 46)
          - National Broadcasting Co., 1958-1959 (Box 46)
          - Peerce, Jan, 1959-1961 (Box 46)
    - Opera, general, 1959-1961 (Box 47)
    - Catalogue of Amer. Operas (Interlochen Press)
      - Correspondence, 1958-1961; 2 folders (Box 47)
      - Corrections for future edition, largely printed, circa, 1958-1959; 2 folders (Box 47)
    - Other Subjects
      - American Federation of Musicians, 1958-1961 (Box 47)
      - Broadcasting
        - General, 1960-1962 (Box 47)
        - Networks
          - American Broadcasting Co., 1959-1962 (Box 47)
          - Columbia Broadcasting System, 1961 (Box 47)
          - National Broadcasting Co., 1959-1962 (Box 47)
        - Stations
          - Chicago (WGN), 1961 (Box 47)